So, Elon Musk recently posted that X
algorithm is now public. It's updated on
GitHub and there is a lot to break down
into how this algorithm works and I
spent a lot of time in order to
understand what I wanted to show to you
in this video. All right, so over here
you can see this tweet which is very
recent announces that this X algorithm
is now public and if you open this
GitHub repository, you're going to see a
bunch of things including things like
thunder, phoenix. So, these are all
parts of the algorithm for X which is
the social media platform. And you can
basically look inside this in order to
understand how the posts are
recommended, what sort of attributes or
information is given to the model which
recommends the post and there are a
couple of things which are actually not
covered in this algorithm which I will
cover about as well. So, I'm going to
start with basics over here, things that
I have understood looking at the code
and talking to large language models and
seeing like what's going on. I want to
give you a journey of a post on X.
Specifically, take a look at this post
from yesterday which has about a million
views and about 7,000 likes, right? So,
it we can say that it falls in the
category of post going viral. So, I'm
going to walk you through how a post
like this works step-by-step based on
the algorithm information that we have
from open-source algorithm today. Now,
first of all, first things first, what
you have to understand is that the whole
algorithm works fundamentally on certain
things like triggers or actions, right?
So, a lot of these things that you see
are actions over here. For example, this
comment box that you see doing a reply
is an action. You know, doing this
retweet is an action or a quote tweet.
Liking a post or marking this as
favorite, how they use it internally, is
an action. Bookmarking it is one,
sharing is one and even some of these
actions which are not really visible to
you. When you click on this these three
dots, you will see that there are things
like not interested or, you know, just
muting the user or blocking the user.
All of these are also actions. So, some
of them, like these ones, are generally
positive actions because if you're
liking or bookmarking, that denotes
that, you know this is like an important
post or something that you like and
these one obviously are negative actions
if you are suggesting you know that this
is not a good post or you know not
interested in this category of post. So
the algorithm mostly operates on these
triggers and actions which you as an end
user take on a post. So let me explain
you what is the journey of a post,
right? So let's say this is a post,
let's say XYZ 1 2 3, whatever you posted
on Twitter. This is a post that you hit
and you hit this post button over here.
Now the moment you post this, the moment
you hit post over here, this is
delivered to a Kafka queue which is
ingested by a component that they call
as Thunder, right? And all of this is in
their algorithm. Now I'm going to skip a
lot of details so that it makes sense to
you without getting too mathematical or
technical, but what happens here is that
Thunder is one system inside X and then
there is a second system called as
Phoenix. And this is not the framework
that we know of Elixir, this is actually
a system that is named like Phoenix
inside X. Thunder is a system that is
responsible for doing in network
suggestions or work rather I should say.
What this means is that for example,
let's say you are following a bunch of
people, right? So over here you are here
and you are following let's say this
person A and you're following this
person B, right? So let's say if person
A like me for example made this tweet
and you're following me, then Thunder
would be the system that would deliver
this tweet on your timeline, right?
Phoenix is a system that works. This is
in network and this one is out of
network. So what this means is that if
you saw this tweet over here yesterday
and you are not following me on X, then
this tweet was delivered to you via the
Phoenix network, not via the Thunder
network. Now generally speaking a post
which is as viral as this would not be
viral only on the basis of Thunder
network, right? Because obviously like
most people on X don't have followers in
millions. So, you cannot feasibly get
close to million impressions based on
just your follower network until and
unless you are somebody like a celebrity
or Elon Musk or somebody who has
hundreds, tens of millions of followers
like a prime minister of a country or
anyone who has big following. This is
going to be limited for you. That means
this is the network that is responsible
to convert any post into a viral post.
Now, see the core idea is that all of
this process is mathematical and
mechanical, right? There is no human
involved as such. So, this has to be all
math and ML and you know, recommendation
and so on and so forth. Thunder is a
simple system. The people you follow
would have a bunch of these posts
visible to you on their timeline and
Phoenix is a ML system which is like
machine learning where it's going to
recommend people outside of your network
as well. Now, let's take a look at how
this happens and what is not exactly
open source in X algorithm which is
released on GitHub. So, going back to
this part where you posted it, it lands
into a Kafka queue which is then
ingested by this Thunder network. What's
going to happen is that this tweet that
you have would be converted into a
128-dimension
vector. Because again, we have to work
with numbers. We can't work with
strings. Computer don't make a lot of
sense working with strings. And this is
also responsible for delivering this to
the feeds of your followers. Feeds of
followers, right? So, anybody who is
following me would have seen these posts
for the first time. That is why you
would have seen that it's basically
impossible for you to get like instant
likes on a post that you have made from
people who are not following you because
X algorithm does not show your new post
to people who are not following you
because Phoenix is not activated right
away. What happens is that inside these
feeds of followers that you have, one of
your post would appear over here, right?
Let's say this X post that I just posted
about. Now, as people are liking, you
know, retweeting it or you know, just
doing a bunch of more activities, these
actions are monitored by the algorithm,
right? So, it's sort of in an explore
mode. It's giving it to the followers
that I have and it's exploring like what
kind of actions are these people taking
in the first place. And based on these
interactions that they are making, this
vector over here, which is generated for
my post, is updating in real time. This
vector over here, which is a combination
of post ID and user ID over here,
plus all the input that we are getting
from the engagement. And this could be
anything like it could be like, you
know, people recommending, not
recommending this post that I'm not
interested in this, people maybe
blocking me over this post after seeing
that. So, all the positive and negative
engagements that are happening that we
discussed earlier, they would affect the
embedding vector for this specific post.
Now, what happens parallelly is that
this Phoenix network also gets
activated. Right? So, this network over
here, what its job is is slightly more
complex than just delivering to
followers, right? So, it's supposed to
do a bunch of things. First thing it's
supposed to do is that it's supposed to
create something we call as a candidate
pool. Now, this candidate pool is
basically a list of potential posts that
can come into a user's feed. Again,
iterating back to the fact that I
created a post, posted it, it went to
Thunder system over here, and then
instead of let's say feed a follower,
this is one follower that I had, right?
So, this one follower opened the app in
like 1 minutes of time. So, it opened
the app after a minute. This Thunder
network delivered this post that I just
made to this follower, and this follower
liked it, commented on it, whatever like
he loved the post, right? That feed that
net that feedback is taken back into the
network, and this vector gets updated.
At the same time, let's say a bunch of
more followers came into play, and they
are also interacted interacting with my
post using the Thunder system that is
there, right? Now, let's say this is
going on, and you know, it has been
going on for let's say 5, 10 minutes, or
whatever. After a few minutes of time,
what's going to happen is that Phoenix
is also going to come into picture. It's
going to create a candidate pool. Now,
what's a candidate pool? It's basically
a list of potential posts that can be
viewed by me. Now, the core idea here is
that every user on X has a specific user
ID, which makes them part of a specific
cohort, right? So, this it's like an
internal detail, but they use as one of
the first inputs that that they use in
Phoenix is two numbers N and M, which
are part of like big table, right? So,
these are like hashes. So, this is one
of the first input in the in the Phoenix
algorithm. The second input is your last
127 actions on platform, right? And this
point over here, this is what makes
personalization possible. So, whenever,
let's say this person came on the feed,
right? They are, you know, just they
just opened X app. What's going to
happen is by the time that loader is
coming on the screen, right? When when
it shows you like it's loading
something, what's going to happen is
that it's going to make a back-end call
to the algorithm, to the recommendation
algorithm. It's going to take in that
user ID, which is waiting for post. It's
going to take their last 127 actions on
the platform, and they're going to run
this through this AI model, this
artificial intelligence model. This is
not a large language model, by the way.
This is just a machine learning model,
whose sole job is to create, like one of
the jobs is to create this candidate
pool of about 200 posts over here,
right? Now, the way this candidate pool
is created is with dot product, because
remember that we have the post ID, user
ID vectors over here, right? So, we have
these vectors of posts that are there,
and based on the interaction and the
stuff that is happening with every
single post, you are able to create a
bunch of 200 posts which are similar to
things that I like. This This metric
over here gives a rough idea of who I am
and which cohort I belong to. This is
also like something which does not
personalize properly, because this is,
um, you know, you can say that this is
basically, in a way, just to give you an
idea, let's say you have user ID number
1,000, right? What's going to happen is
that X is going to create or give you
two numbers between zero to 1 million,
right? So, these would be two numbers
over here. And these two numbers are
deterministic. These are static for you
when you create it. And this is
basically this collection of two numbers
is a cohort, which is like a broader
thing for you. So, for every For
example, like whenever a new member
joins the platform, they already are
part of one of the cohorts which has
been trained and retrained and you know,
just influenced by other people on the
platform. Their 127 history action is
empty, so their personalization would be
weak. And that is why like, you know,
you don't get personalized post if you
are just signed up. But this part over
here, this makes it possible to
personalize your actions because, you
know, these actions, for example, what
you have liked, what you have
bookmarked, what you have retweeted, and
so on and so forth. So, 127
recent actions that you have done on the
platform are fed into this algorithm.
And based on this algorithm and the
overall posts that are existing on the X
network, it's going to give you a
candidate pool of post to pick from.
Now, this includes a bunch of interests
of people. This includes, you know, what
they have done recently on the platform.
This is basically a list of personalized
post. And what we don't have inside the
open-source algorithm is this box over
here. So, you see that this box over
here, this algorithm, this machine
learning algorithm is a black box for us
because this has been trained somehow,
right? This is same for every user. It's
not like you're going to get a different
machine learning algorithm per user.
It's the same algorithm for every single
user on X. The only thing differs are
the inputs to this algorithm, which is
like your activity on the platform and
your static constant user ID mapping in
a huge table. Now, because this is a
black box, you cannot really predict
what's going on here because this is
like, you know, just like with large
language models, we have, um, you know,
these are effectively black boxes. If
you look at any open-weight model, you
can't really tell if they are trained on
proprietary data or not until and
unless, you know, they are just spitting
out some proprietary data directly. It's
basically impossible to just inspect
their weights, which are just numbers,
right? These are like random numbers
over here, which are the weights that
you basically download. So, the same
thing exists here that this thing over
here is a bunch of collection of
weights, which is a black box because we
don't know how it has been trained in
the first place and what these weights
are even in the first place because all
we have is just the code like the open
source code, right? Not even the weights
in this case. So, we don't have the
machine learning algorithm to mimic like
what's going to happen. And then it just
creates like a bunch of these candidate
polls candidate pool, which has a bunch
of these posts. And now these posts, for
example, this one that I the post that I
created over here yesterday, this could
be part of this one of the 200 posts
which has which is there. And the more
people, for example, these set of people
also interacted with it, right? So, the
algorithm effectively got it right that
it knows that it served the right user
the right post. What's going to happen
is that the more this positive feedback
loop gets created, the sharper this
vector embedding becomes for that
specific cohort. So, it's going to show
it to more and more people in that
specific cohort and that is how posts
take off. That is how, you know, you end
up with almost a million views on a
single post, which is less than 1 day
old. Now, of course, this is not the
full picture. I've just given you a very
small window into like how posts and
how, you know, a single post reaches
your timeline. What happens is that once
these 200 posts are created and once the
Thunder Network are also there, all of
them are combined together because you
see that inside the For You tab, which
is there on Twitter, this is by the way
this algorithm that I just told you
about, this is only for the For You tab,
right? This place over here is a mix of
followers post plus, you know, broader
network, which is the which is the
outside network. So, the posts
recommended by your machine learning
candidate pool over here and the post
over here, which are recommended by
Thunder, are combined and then they are
sorted again for relevance. You know,
and then and only then then they are
delivered to your timeline over here.
Now, see, inherently, it's not possible
to generate a recipe for, you know, a
post virality. So, it's not like you
include a bunch of keywords and then
it'll become viral because you if you
look at this carefully, you're going to
see that none of these networks are
actually prioritizing your content only
on the basis of what the content is in
the first place. I'm not saying that
this vector over here, this post vector
is of itself, so it's doing a dot
product to figure out like if this is
the right thing or not. What they are
prioritizing more is on the interactions
done by a specific cohort of people,
right? So, if people who like a lot of,
you know, in this case in this post if
people who like a lot of bun and, you
know, maybe like rust, for example, as a
keyword and, you know, million line
change PR, these sort of things, they
would automatically have these candidate
pools generated which includes topics of
those sorts, right? And if X saw I'm
going to recommend this to a few people
inside this post just to see like what's
going on and all of them or at least
most of them are responding positively,
then the platform puts it into exploit
mode, right? Which is where it'll try to
expand your audience and it'll try to
show that post to more and more people.
And because this is fundamentally built
on how people react to your post, there
is no way to actually like engineer
virality until and unless, of course,
you don't have a lot of followers in the
first place, right? So, if you have a
lot of followers like I have I don't
have a lot of followers. I have around
28, 30,000 followers. But if you have
somebody has like 1 million plus
followers and if they write something
interesting, then the chances of them
going viral are far higher because the
Thunder system that exists in the first
place, it's an in-network system that
avoids all this um things, right? Of ML
and dot products and so on and so forth.
It's an easy way to give some of these
posts some visibility in the first
candidate pool that is created, right?
Because Thunder network also has
priority in this. People who you follow
have priority in this. In fact, Twitter
has a dedicated following tab in the
first place, right? So, if not for you,
people will always discover you with
following tab if they are on that. So,
yeah, that is sort of like a mini look
inside X algorithm. It obviously gets a
lot more complex than what I have
explained, but this more or less is the
foundation of how they are making all of
this work. The core idea of the
algorithm itself, like how does it
recommend in the first place, is that it
wants to maximize these positive actions
from people, right? That is why it would
recommend it. If people are forcing more
or doing more of negative actions, it
will just kill your post. That is why if
you would have seen, like, I don't know
if you have seen this or not, but you
can do a rage bait on X, or you know,
you can just create posts which are
negative, they would get a spike because
they would quickly get a lot of likes,
let's say, but they would also get
negative reactions. People are blocking,
people are muting. So, in the long term,
I feel that would not be a wise strategy
to grow your account. In order to grow
your account, you'd want posts like this
which have majorly positive reaction
from the algorithm so that it keeps
pushing your account and the tweets that
you are doing among the audience. Now,
I'm pretty sure that there would be some
parts or some things that are hidden,
obviously, like some things that we
obviously know, like the Phoenix weights
and, you know, how this works internally
is how it is trained internally is not
known to us, but I'm pretty sure that
there would be other things as well
which are hidden. This algorithm that is
open source to us you can't really
confirm that this is the actual code
that's also running in the X algorithm,
right? On the back end. You just have to
trust us, trust them. Um, but I think
this is good enough, right? If they're
saying and if they're doing a lot of
this code, it's very hard for them to
actually create a completely different
algorithm. Yes, there would be some more
things on top of this, maybe like they
have given some special account access
or, you know, government account or gray
checks access differently in some
specific ways which we don't know about,
but more or less, for us common people,
this is like a interesting algorithm
breakdown. There are a lot of things,
you know, if you if you run this through
Grok, you will see a bunch of more
suggestions what you should do, what you
should not do, but I just found that
this is interesting because it helped me
understand like why some posts go viral,
why some posts don't go viral. And the
core idea is that you just have to make
content that is good and that is
relatable to your initial followers,
right? And that means that ideally you
should stick to your niche because if
you're talking outside of your niche,
maybe it's a great tweet, but you would
not get the Phoenix network to activate
until unless your thunder network itself
is not, you know, giving strong results.
There could be exceptions, obviously,
like I mentioned, you know, it's not
like a foolproof system because we don't
really know how this is working and
machine learning models are obviously
like they are not fully deterministic.
You can get different outputs on
different inputs, on same inputs rather.
So, um so yeah, but but generally
speaking, a few tips if you want to take
away if you're trying to grow on X and
if you want to see like what what's
working is that I would say first of
all, stick to your niche. Second is
that, you know, engage with your
followers so that they engage back more.
This is something I'm also guilty of. I
just, you know, post tweets in my free
time and then just forgot forget to look
at them. But this would help, right?
Because the reason it would help is
because the next tweets that they you
would add, they would engage with that,
right? So, it will give you further
boost. And third is, of course, like
avoid tweets that would result in people
taking aggressive actions, right? So,
for example, I mean, if you're just
solely focusing on growth, I would avoid
tweets that are like too much
polarizing, so much that people just end
up blocking you in the first place,
right? Because that is a huge negative
signal. So, yeah, you can be
opinionated. I'm not saying that you
have to fake it, but you can always
engineer the language in such a way that
if your block rate is 50%, let's just
say it drops to 10%. So, yeah, that's
pretty much it for this video. I guess
that is that gives you a little bit of
understanding on how the X algorithm
works. This is the only algorithm I
think that we have which is like a major
website which is open-source, but not
quite fully because of two reasons, of
course. First is that we don't know what
is this machine learning model exactly
and how this is trained and how this is
updated also and what are the weights.
And second is, of course, like we don't
really know if this is the exact code
which is running in production or this
is like a trimmed down cleaned up fork
of the code. But, yeah, that's pretty
much it. Do let me know in the comments
what do you think. So, that's all for
this video. Hopefully, you liked it. If
you did, make sure to leave a like and
subscribe to the channel. I'm going to
see you in the next video very soon. If
you're still watching, make sure you
leave a comment I watched till the end
below to tell me that you were still
here and let me know what do you think
about the video.